All right, let's talk about computer architecture.
Now, what is computer architecture?
You've probably heard about architecture before
when people are talking about skyscrapers
and hospitals and museums and stuff like that.
Well, computer architecture is actually pretty simple.
There's lots of different kinds of buildings,
lots of different kinds of computers,
and you wouldn't architect a home
the same way you wouldn't architect a car wash,
and you wouldn't architect a museum,
the same way you do our restaurant.
Well, there's different types of computers.
You wouldn't architect them exactly the same either
because each one has its own specific set of needs
and purposes, just like the buildings.
So, there's certain things you need to take into consideration
when thinking about computer architecture.
It's these set of rules and methods
that describe the functionality, organization,
and implementation of the computer system.
Now, this includes hardware, software,
and everything in between and all around it.
Let's talk about hardware.
When we talk about hardware,
we're talking about the stuff you can physically see and touch.
Stuff like CPUs, memory, hard drives, network cards,
IO adapters, the graphical processing unit,
all that kind of stuff.
The stuff that you can pick up, take a look at
and shove back into the computer.
Don't shove it back into the computer.
Place it gently.
We're talking about software.
That's the stuff that we can't see.
That stuff like programs that are written in code,
operating systems, built-in programs like Notepad,
applications you're right, libraries,
ones you download, tools, utilities, programs,
all sorts of stuff.
And you can think about the operating system
as the primary program,
and everything else just goes through it.
So there are instances when you're gonna write software
that sits directly on top of the hardware
that doesn't use the operating system.
Those do exist, but most of the time,
the operating system is there in the middle,
making sure not only this stuff is easier to write,
but that it's gonna run safer as well.
All right, let's get into these computer
architecture components.
Earlier I talked about how architecture computer
is a lot like the architecture of a building.
Lots of different buildings, lots of different computers.
Now a building typically has a couple of things in common.
It's got walls, it's got a roof, got floor,
hallway, it probably has an electrical system,
probably plumbing, windows, doors.
You can see there's a lot of stuff to think about there.
In computer architecture, you've got a series of components.
And the architecture is all about how they are designed
to work well with another and fit together
so that it performs as a bank or as a museum again.
And we can kind of see this in computer architecture as well.
And there's this split between the hardware
and the software side.
So let's start with software design.
Software design includes the compiler,
firmware, operating system, applications.
The hardware design includes physical, circuit,
digital design, data path control,
instruction set procedures, and IO systems.
Let's start by talking about the software.
Now, you can generally split software
into two distinct flavors.
There is application software and the system software.
Application software is what you generally call an app,
short for application.
You start it, it runs, it does its thing.
And when it's done and you don't need it anymore,
you just stop it and it goes away.
It generally interacts with you,
or maybe another user or a file,
but it typically sits on top of the operating system.
And it's going to use the operating system
to get the data it needs, to access memory,
to talk to the network, all that kind of stuff.
Now, system software is the code that runs
as part of the operating system, generally.
Without the system software,
you wouldn't be able to run any sort of application software.
Because generally, it's the application software
telling the system software what it wants.
And then there's firmware.
Firmware generally gets written to read-only memory.
And it comes from the factory associated
with that piece of hardware.
And you're not going to change it
unless there's like a problem that needs to get fixed,
or there's a new feature coming out.
You can upgrade the firmware to get that.
The firmware provides a common set of methods
for doing things, that the operating system is going to use.
Let's take a step back and see what we have so far, right?
Because we've talked about a lot of stuff.
We have the application software.
That's the app, right?
And that sits on top of the operating system,
the system software.
But there's actually a step before that,
because you have to build the application.
So you're right the application in software language,
like Java, C++, something like that.
Now, I can write some code,
and you can probably take a look at it
and see what I'm trying to do.
The computer itself doesn't understand this yet
until we run it through something called a compiler.
A compiler takes source code,
which is the stuff that I write,
and then compiles it into something machine can run.
That's called object code.
And it's a one-way direction.
You can't take object code and then break it apart
into its source code.
It's kind of like bake in a cake.
You can't take a cake and turn it back into its ingredients.
It's the kind of the finished product there.
So that's how you make an application, or a cake.
Okay, so we've got our compiler,
we've got an application,
we've got the operating system.
And then before that, before it actually hits the hardware,
we've got something called the instruction set,
which is part of the instruction set architecture,
another aspect of computer architecture.
And this is ultimately what bridges the gap
between the software and the hardware.
The instruction set is basically everything
that the computer's processor is capable of doing.
It lists out every single function it can do.
I can compare these two numbers together,
tell you which one's greater,
or if they're equal, add these two numbers together,
store this data over here, move this data over there.
It's nothing too fancy,
but these are the small building blocks
that you can use to make these higher level fancy applications
from.
Now, ultimately everything we're doing right now
is so that we can get something onto the processor.
So the processor can run this application, right?
That's why we're doing all this stuff.
You've probably seen a processor too,
you're thinking about this,
it's a square chip thing with a whole bunch of metal
pins on the bottom of it.
Well, those metal pins aren't just for traction,
they're there because they hook into the motherboard
or the back plane of the computer,
and we have to send electrical impulses through it.
That's how we tell the chip,
or the processor, what we want it to do,
and then we want to get the answer
of what those two numbers added together are.
We have to do a read, so we know
we have to know which pins to read from, right?
There's a whole lot of stuff to understand there,
and that's all documented in the instruction set.
Now, you can picture a calculator as a type of computer.
A phone is a type of computer,
a supercomputer is a type of computer.
Three different types of computers,
three different architectures,
three different instruction sets, right?
So we need to ultimately need a compiler
for each one of those, right?
The blueprints for all that are contained
within the instruction set,
and part of the instruction set architecture.
Even a very simple couple lines of code program,
like add these things together,
it has to take quite a journey to get from something
that I can describe to something
that can be represented electronically on a CPU.
And then there's a whole other area of physical design
that describes building the logic gates and physical chips.
That falls under digital design,
circuit implementation, and physical implementation.
And believe me, that goes off pretty far
in its own direction.
We've covered a lot here,
from stuff you can see to stuff you run,
to stuff you're right, to stuff that you,
stuff that you just kind of have to trust that it's there
because there's no way a computer would work without it.
And there's definitely a near infinite number of ways
you could architect a computer.
Hopefully the computer you're using right now
was built for a specific purpose,
and it does it really, really well.
In the next lesson, we're gonna talk about a computer
that's been architected specifically
to run business transactions.
And that's the IBM Z.